<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Spadacrene Anglica, the English spaw, or, The glory of Knaresborough springing from several famous fountains there adjacent, called the vitrioll, sulphurous and dropping wels; and also other minerall waters. Their nature, physical use, situation, and many admirable cures being exactly exprest in the subsequent treatise of the learned Dr. Dean, and the sedulous observations of the ingenious Michael Stanhope Esquire. Wherein it is proved by reason and experience, that the vitrioline fountain is equall (and not inferiour) to the Germain spaw.</title>
            <author>Deane, Edmund, 1582?-1640.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1654</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 89 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 24 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A82022</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing D491A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R226651</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99899680</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99899680</idno>
            <idno type="VID">135135</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A82022)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 135135)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2427:7)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Spadacrene Anglica, the English spaw, or, The glory of Knaresborough springing from several famous fountains there adjacent, called the vitrioll, sulphurous and dropping wels; and also other minerall waters. Their nature, physical use, situation, and many admirable cures being exactly exprest in the subsequent treatise of the learned Dr. Dean, and the sedulous observations of the ingenious Michael Stanhope Esquire. Wherein it is proved by reason and experience, that the vitrioline fountain is equall (and not inferiour) to the Germain spaw.</title>
                  <author>Deane, Edmund, 1582?-1640.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 45, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed by Tho. Broad, and are to be sold in his shop in the lower end of Stonegate, near to the common hall gates,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>York :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1654.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Royal College of Surgeons Library, London.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Mineral waters --  England --  Knaresborough --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Medicine --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-12</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-12</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:135135:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:135135:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>Spadacrene Anglica, <hi>The Engliſh Spaw,</hi> OR, The glory of Knaresborough, <hi>Springing from ſeveral famous Fountains there adjacent, called the Vitrioll, Sulphurous and dropping Wels; and alſo other Mineral Waters.</hi> Their nature, Phyſical uſe, Situation, and many admirable Cures being exactly expreſt in the ſubſequent Treatiſe of the learned Dr. <hi>Dean,</hi> and the ſedulous obſervations of the ingenious <hi>Michael Stanhope</hi> Eſquire. <hi>Wherein it is proved by Reaſon and Expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience, that the Vitrioline Fountain is equall (and not inferiour) to the</hi> Germain Spaw.</p>
            <q>
               <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>.</q>
            <p>
               <hi>York,</hi> Printed by <hi>Tho. Broad,</hi> and are to be ſold in his Shop in the lower end of Stonegate, near to the Common Hall Gates. 1654.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="treatise">
            <pb facs="tcp:135135:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="1" facs="tcp:135135:2"/>
               <head>The Engliſh SPAW.</head>
               <byline>Written by Dr. <hi>Edm. Dean,</hi> late Phyſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cian in <hi>Yorke.</hi>
               </byline>
               <div n="1" type="chapter">
                  <head>
                     <hi>CHAP. I.</hi> Of the ſituation of the Town of <hi>Knaresborow.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">G</seg>Naresbrugh</hi> (commonly called <hi>Knaresborow</hi>) is a very ancient Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ket Town in the Weſt-Riding of <hi>Yorkeſhire,</hi> diſtant 14 miles from the City of <hi>Yorke;</hi> where the Pole is elevated 54 degrees, and 20 odde minutes. On the South-weſt part thereof is that fair, and goodly Fort, ſo much renown<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, both for the pleaſant ſituation, and remarkable ſtrength, known by the name of <hi>Knaresborow Castle,</hi> ſeated on a moſt ragged and rough Rock; whence (as learned Mr. <hi>Cambden</hi> ſaith) it is ſo named.</p>
                  <p>Both the Caſtle and Town are fenced on the South and Weſt parts with the Rivers <hi>N<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>de:</hi> which is beauti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied herewith two fair Bridges of ſtone, which lead from the Town into the Forreſt adjoyning, as alſo unto a larg empaled Park of his Majeſties, called <hi>Bilton-Park,</hi> well ſtored with fallow Deer: part whereof is bordered with the ſaid river.</p>
                  <pb n="2" facs="tcp:135135:3"/>
                  <p>The Town it ſelf ſtandeth on a hill, having almoſt on every ſide an aſcent to it; and about it are divers fruitfull valleys well repleniſhed with graſſe, corn and wood. The waters there are wholſome and clear; the ayre dry and pure. In brief, there is nothing wanting, that may fitly ſerve for a good and commodious habi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, and the content and entertainment of ſtrangers.</p>
                  <p>Many things are very obſervable in this place, which becauſe they rather doe appertain to the volumnes of Geographers, and Antiquaries, then to the purpoſe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended in this little treatiſe, are here omitted.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="chapter">
                  <head>
                     <hi>CHAP. II.</hi> Of the ſeverall earths, ſtones, and minerals, found neer and about this place.</head>
                  <p>ALthough there are in ſundry places of this king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, as many or more ſeveral kindes, and ſorts of earths, quarries of ſtone, minerals, and mines of mettals, then in any other Realm whatſoever; not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding, no one place hath been obſerved to have them either in ſuch plenty, or variety in ſo ſmall a di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance as this. For here is found not onely white and yellow marble, plaiſter, oker, rud, rubrick, free-ſtone, and hard greet-ſtone, a ſoft reddiſh ſtone, iron-ſtone, brim-ſtone, vitreal, nitre, allum, lead, copper, (and without doubt, divers mixtures of theſe) but alſo many other minerals might (perhaps) be found out by the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligent ſearch, and skilfull induſtry of thoſe, who would take pains to labour a little herein.</p>
                  <p>All which doe manifeſtly demonſtrate, that nature hath ſtored this little territory with a greater diverſity of hidden benefits, then great and ſpacious Countries otherwiſe abounding in outward native commodities, and that the fountains, or ſprings of water hereabouts cannot otherwiſe then participate of their ſeveral na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures and properties.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="chapter">
                  <pb n="3" facs="tcp:135135:3"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>CHAP. III.</hi> Of the fountains, of pure and ſimple waters, neer and about the Town.</head>
                  <p>AS generally moſt part of the Weſt Riding of <hi>York<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhire</hi> (eſpecially the hilly and more mountainous places thereof) are ſtored with fountains and ſprings of clear, limpid and pure ſimple waters; ſo likewiſe the territory hereabouts is not without plenty of them. Two whereof have gotten and purchaſed that reputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, as to be Sainted: The one called by the name of Saint <hi>Magnus,</hi> or <hi>Magnus-well:</hi> the other, that of Saint <hi>Roberts.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Theſe, formerly for a year, or two, have been in great requeſt in theſe parts amongſt the common ſort, much ſought unto by many, and great concourſe of peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple have daily gathered and flocked to them, both near, and afarre off, as is moſt commonly ſeen, when any new thing is firſt found out, <hi>Fama enim creſcit eundo,</hi> even unto incredible wonders and miracles, or rather fictions, and lyes. All which commeth to paſſe as we may well ſuppoſe, through our over much Engliſh cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulity, or as I may better ſay) rather ſuperſtition. For to any ſuch like Well, will ſwarm at firſt both young and old (eſpecially the female ſex, as ever more apt to be deluded) halt, lame, blinde, deaf, dumb, yea, almoſt all, and that for all manner of maladies and diſeaſes, both inward and outward.</p>
                  <p>But for as much, as theſe are ſprings of pure, and ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple waters meerly, without any mixture at all of mine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rals, to make them become medicinable, it is verily thought, that the many and ſeveral cures, which have been attributed unto them in thoſe times, when they were ſo frequented, were rather fained and imaginary, then true and real; and that thoſe, who then viſited them, were deſirous (either to uphold and maintain the credit, and reputation of their Saints, or elſe, to avoid the ſcorn and deriſion of their own deluſion) to have o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers likewiſe deceived.</p>
                  <pb n="4" facs="tcp:135135:4"/>
                  <p>Time hath quite worn all their ſtrength, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumed all their virtues; ſo that nothing of worth now remains with them, ſaving onely their bare names and titles:
<q>Sic magna ſua mole ruunt.</q>
                  </p>
                  <p>Wherefore to omit theſe, as ſcarce worthy the men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioning; thoſe are chiefly here to be deſcribed, which do participate of mineral vertues, and faculties.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="chapter">
                  <head>
                     <hi>CHAP. IV.</hi> Of five fountains near unto the town, which do parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipate of mineral virtues.</head>
                  <p>OUt of the divers Fountains ſpringing hereabouts, five are worthy the obſervation of Phyſitians. The firſt whereof is very near unto the river bank, over a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Caſtle, called by the name of the <hi>Dropping-well,</hi> for that it droppeth, diſtilleth, and trickleth down from the hanging rock above. The water whereof hath a certain quality or property to turn any thing that lieth in it, into a ſtony ſubſtance in a very ſhort ſpace.</p>
                  <p>Three of the others (being all of them much of one, and the ſame nature) are termed by the country peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple thereabouts the <hi>Stinkingwels,</hi> in regard they have an ill, and fetide ſmel, conſiſting moſt of Sulphure-vive, or quick brimſtone. One of them, and that which hath the greateſt current, or ſtream of water, is in <hi>Bilton park</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The other two are in the ſaid Forreſt; one is neare unto the Town; the other is further off, almoſt two miles from it, beyond a place called <hi>Haregate head,</hi> in a bottome on the right hand of it, as you go, and almoſt in the ſide of a little brook.</p>
                  <p>The fift, and laſt (for which I have principally un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertaken to write this ſhort Diſcourſe) is an acide, or tart fountain in the ſaid Forreſt, commonly named by the vulgar ſort, <hi>Tuewhit-well,</hi> and the <hi>Engliſh Spaw,</hi>
                     <pb n="5" facs="tcp:135135:4"/> by thoſe of the better rank, in imitation of thoſe two moſt famous acide fountains at the <hi>Spaw</hi> in <hi>Germany,</hi> to wit, <hi>Sauuenir,</hi> and <hi>Pouhon:</hi> whereof the firſt being the prime one) is half a league from the <hi>Spa,</hi> or <hi>Spaw</hi> Village; the other is in the middle of the town.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="5" type="chapter">
                  <head>
                     <hi>CHAP. V.</hi> A more particular recitall of the firſt four wels.</head>
                  <p>I Purpoſe to ſpeak ſomewhat more in this place of the firſt foure Springs mentioned in the former Chapter, in regard the conſideration of them may perhaps give ſome light to thoſe, who ſhall hereafter ſearch further into the ſecrets, which nature may ſeem to afford in the Country hereabouts.</p>
                  <p>The firſt is the <hi>Dropping well,</hi> known almoſt to all who have travelled unto this place. The water where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of diſtilleth and trickleth down from the hanging Rock over it, not onely dropping wiſe, but alſo falling in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny pretty little ſtreams.</p>
                  <p>This water iſſueth at firſt out of the earth, not far from the ſaid hanging Rock, and running a while in one entire current, continueth ſo, till it commeth al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt to the brim of the crag; where being oppoſed by a damme (as it were artificial) of certain ſpongy ſtones, is afterwards divided into many ſmaller branches, and falleth from on high in manner aforeſaid.</p>
                  <p>It is therefore very like that Mr. <hi>Cambden</hi> in perſon did not ſee this fountain, but rather that he had it by re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation from others; or at leaſt wiſe (if he did ſee it) that he did not mark, and duly obſerve the originall ſpringing up of the water, when in his <hi>Britannia</hi> he ſaith thus: <hi>The waters thereof ſpring not up out of the veins of the earth, &amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Concerning the properties and qualities thereof, I have nothing more to write at this time (there being
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:135135:5"/> formerly little triall had of it) ſaving that divers inha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitants thereabouts ſay, and affirm, that it hath been found to be very effectuall in ſtaying any flux of the body: which thing I eaſily believe.</p>
                  <p>The other three are ſulphurous fountains, and caſt forth a ſtinking ſmell a-farre off, eſpecially in the Win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſeaſon, and when the weather is coldeſt. They are all noiſome to ſmell to, and cold to touch, without any manifeſt or actual heat at all; by reaſon (as may moſt probably be thought) their mines and veins of brim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtone, are not kindled under the earth; being (perhaps) hindred by the mixture of ſalt therewith.</p>
                  <p>Thoſe who drink of their waters, relate, they verily think there is gun-powder in them, and that now and then they vomit after drinking thereof.</p>
                  <p>The waters as they run along the earth, do leave be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hind them on the graſſe and leaves, a gray ſlimy ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, which being ſet on fire, hath the right ſavour of common brimſtone. They are much haunted with Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geons, an argument of much ſalt in them; of which in the evaporation of the water by fire, we found a good quantity remaining in the bottom of the veſſel.</p>
                  <p>One thing further was worth obſervation; that white mettall (as ſilver) dipped into them, preſently ſeemeth to reſemble copper: which we firſt noted by putting a ſil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver porrenger into one of theſe; unto which Sir <hi>Fran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cis Traps</hi> did firſt bring us. Which tincture theſe wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters give by reaſon of their ſulphur.</p>
                  <p>Touching their vertues, and effects, there may in ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral the like properties be aſcribed unto them, as are attributed unto other ſulphurous Bathes actually cold, participating alſo of Salt.</p>
                  <p>The vulgar ſort drink theſe waters (as they ſay) to expell reef, and fellon; yea, many who are much trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled with itches, ſcabs, morphews, tetters, ring-worms, and the like, are ſoon holpen and cured, by waſhing the parts ill-affected therewith. Which thing they might
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:135135:5"/> much more conveniently and more commodiouſly do, if at that in <hi>Bilton</hi> park, were framed to capacious Bathes; the one cold, the other<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> to be made hot, or warm by art, for certain known houres a day.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="6" type="chapter">
                  <head>
                     <hi>CHAP. VI.</hi> A more particular deſcription of the fifth, or laſt Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain, called the <hi>Engliſh Spaw.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>THis, being the principal ſubject of this whole Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe, is in the ſaid Forreſt, about half a league, or a mile and a half, Weſt from the Town; from whence there is almoſt a continuall riſing to it, but nothing ſo great as the aſcent, is from the Spaw village to the <hi>Sau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venir.</hi> This here ſpringeth out of a mountainous ground, and almoſt at the height of the aſcent, at <hi>Harc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gate-head;</hi> having a great deſcent on both ſides the ridge thereof; and the Country thereabouts ſomewhat reſembleth that at the <hi>Spaw</hi> in <hi>Germany.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The firſt diſcoverer of it to have any medicinal qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity (ſo far forth as I can learn) was one Mr. <hi>William Slingsby,</hi> a Gentleman of many good parts, of an anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent and worthy Family neer thereby; who having tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velled in his younger t me, was throughly acquainted with the taſte, uſe, and faculties of the two Spaw Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains.</p>
                  <p>In his latter time, about 55 years ago, it was his good Fortune to live for a little while at a Grange houſe very neer to this Fountain, and afterwards in <hi>Bilton</hi> Park all his life long. Who drinking of this water, found it in all things to agree with thoſe at the Spaw. Whereupon (greatly rejoycing at ſo good and fortunate an accident) he made ſome further trial and aſſay. That done, he cauſed the Fountain to be well and artificially walled about, and paved at the bottom, (as it is now at this day) with two fair ſtone flags, with a fit hole in the ſide thereof, for the free paſſage of the water through a little guttered ſtone.</p>
                  <pb n="8" facs="tcp:135135:6"/>
                  <p>It is open at the top, and walled ſomewhat higher than the earth, as well to keep out filth, as cattell for com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming and approaching to it. It is foure ſquare, three foot wide, and the water within is about three quarters of a yard deep.</p>
                  <p>Firſt, we cauſed it to be laded dry, as well to ſcoure it, as alſo to ſee the riſing up of the water, which we found to ſpring up onely at the bottome at the chink, or cranny, between two ſtones, ſo left purpoſely for the ſpringing up of the water at the bottome: Which (as <hi>Pliny</hi> obſerveth in his 31 Book of his Natural Hiſtory, and the third chapter) is a ſigne above all of the good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of a Fountain.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>And above all</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>one thing would be obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, and ſeen unto, that the ſource which feedeth it, ſpring and boile up directly from the bottome, and not iſſue forth at the ſides: which alſo is a main point that concerneth the perpetuity thereof, and whereby we may collect, that it will held ſtill, and be never drawn dry.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The ſtream of water which paſſeth away by the hole in the ſide thereof, is much one, and about the propor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the current of <hi>Sauuenir.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The above-named Gentleman did drink the water of this Fountain every year after, all his life time, for helping his infirmities, and maintaing of his health, and would oftentimes ſay and aver, that it was much bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and did excell the tart fountains beyond the Seas, as being more quick and lively, and fuller of Mine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall ſpirits; effecting his operation more ſpeedily, and ſooner paſſing through the Body.</p>
                  <p>Moreover, Dr. <hi>Timothy bright</hi> of happy memory, a learned Phyſitian, while he lived, my very kind freind, and familiar acquaintance, firſt gave the name of the <hi>Engl ſh Spaw</hi> unto this Fountain, about thirty years ſince or more. For he alſo formerly had ſpent ſome time at the <hi>Spaw</hi> in <hi>Germany;</hi> ſo that he was very able to compare thoſe with this of ours. Nay, he had fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thermore
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:135135:6"/> ſo good an opinion, and ſo high a conceit of this, that he did not onely direct and adviſe others to it, but himſelf alſo (for moſt part) would uſe it in the Summer ſeaſon.</p>
                  <p>Likewiſe Dr. <hi>Anthony Hunton</hi> lately of <hi>Newark</hi> upon <hi>Trent,</hi> a Phyſitian of no leſſe worth, and happy memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry (to whom for his true love to me, and kind reſpect of me, I was very much beholden) would often expo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtulate with me at our meetings, and with other Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlemen of <hi>Yorkeſhire,</hi> his patients, how it came to paſſe, that I, and the Phyſitians of <hi>Yorke,</hi> did not by publick writing make the fame and worth thereof better known to the world?</p>
               </div>
               <div n="7" type="chapter">
                  <head>
                     <hi>CHAP. VII.</hi> Of the difference of this Fountain from thoſe at the <hi>Spaw,</hi> to wit, <hi>Sauuenir,</hi> and <hi>Pouhon.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>THis ſpringeth almoſt at the top of the aſcent (as formerly hath been ſaid) from a dry and ſomewhat ſandy earth: The water whereof running South<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſt, is very clear, pure, full of life, and mineral exha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations.</p>
                  <p>We find it chiefly to conſiſt of a vitrioline nature and quality, with a participation alſo of thoſe other mine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rals, which are ſaid to be in the <hi>Sauuenir</hi> Fountain; but in a more perfect and exquiſite mixture and tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per (as we deem) and therefore to be ſuppoſed better and nobler then it. The difference between them will be found to be onely <hi>Secundum majus &amp; minus,</hi> that is, according to more, or leſſe, which maketh no diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence in kind, but in degrees. This partaketh in grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter meaſure of the qualities, and leſſer of the ſubſtances of the Minerals, then that doth; and for that cauſe it is of a more quick and ſpeedy operation; as alſo for the ſame reaſon, his tenuity of body, and fulneſſe of mineral ſpirits therein contained, it cannot be ſo farre
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:135135:7"/> tranſported from its own ſource and ſpring, without loſſe and diminution of his ſtrength and goodneſſe. For being carried no further then to the Town it ſelf (though the glaſſe or veſſel be cloſely ſtopt) it becommeth ſom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what weaker: if as far as to <hi>York,</hi> much more: but if 20 or 30 miles further, it will then be found to be of ſmall force or validity, as we have often obſerved.</p>
                  <p>Whereas contrariwiſe the water of the lower Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain at the <hi>Spaw,</hi> called <hi>Pouhon,</hi> is frequently and u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſually carried and conveyed into other countries afar off, and remote, as into <hi>France, England, Scotland, Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> and to divers parts of <hi>Germany,</hi> and unto ſome parts of <hi>Italy;</hi> Yea, and that of <hi>Sauvenir,</hi> (which is the better Fountain, and whoſe water cannot be carried ſo far away, as the other may) is oftentimes uſed now a dayes at <hi>Paris,</hi> the chief City of <hi>France.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>But this of ours cannot be ſent away any whit ſo far off, without loſſe and decay of his efficacy and vertue, ſo ayrie, ſubtill, and piercing are its ſpirits and mineral exhalations, that they ſoon paſſe, vaniſh, and fly away. Which thing we have eſteemed to be a principal good ſigne of the worthy properties of this rare Fountain. So that this water, being newly taken up at the Well, and preſently after drunk, cannot otherwiſe, but ſooner paſſe by the Hypochondries, and through the body, and cauſe a ſpeedier effect, then thoſe in <hi>Germany</hi> can. Whereby any one may eaſily collect, and gather, that this getteth his ſoveraign faculties better in its paſſage by and through the variety of minerals included in the earth (which onely afford unto it an halitious body) then thoſe do.</p>
                  <p>If then we be deſirous to have this of ours become commodious either for preſerving of our healths, or for altering any diſtemper, or curing any infirmity (for which it is proper and available) it ought chiefly to be taken at the Fountain it ſelf, before the minerall ſpirits be diſſipated.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="8" type="chapter">
                  <pb n="11" facs="tcp:135135:7"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>CHAP. VIII.</hi> That Vitrioll is here more predominant then any other Minerall.</head>
                  <p>WE have ſufficiently been ſatisfied by expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience and trials, through what Minerals this water doth paſſe: but to know in what pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portion they are exactly mixed therewith, it is beyond humane invention to finde out; Nature having reſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved this ſecret to her ſelf alone. Nevertheleſſe it may very well be conjectured, that as in the frame and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition of the moſt noble creature, Man (the leſſer world) there is a temper of the four elements rather <hi>ad juſtitiam</hi> (as the Phyloſophers ſay) then <hi>ad pondus;</hi> ſo Nature in the mixture of theſe Minerals, hath likewiſe taken more of ſome, and leſſe of others, as ſhe thought to be moſt fit and expedient for the good and behoof of mans health, and the recovery and reſtitution of it de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cayed; being indeed ſuch a work, as no Art is able to imitate.</p>
                  <p>That <hi>Vitriolum</hi> (otherwiſe called <hi>Chalcanthum</hi>) is here moſt predominant, there needs no other proof, then from the aſſay of the water it ſelf; which both in the tart and inky ſmack thereof, joyned with a piercing and a pricking quality, and in the ſavour (which is ſom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what a little vitrioline) is altogether like unto the anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent <hi>Spaw</hi> waters: which according to the conſent of all thoſe, who have conſidered their natural compoſitions, do moſt of all, and chiefly participate of vitrioll.</p>
                  <p>Notwithſtanding for a more manifeſt, and ſuller triall hereof, put as much powder of Gals, as will lye on two-pence, or three pence, into a glaſſe full of this wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, newly taken up at the fountain, you ſhall ſee it by and by turned into the right and perfect colour of Cla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ret wine, that is fully ripe, clear, and well fined, which may eaſily deceive the eye of the skilfulleſt Vintner,</p>
                  <pb n="12" facs="tcp:135135:8"/>
                  <p>This demonſtration hath been often made, not with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the admiration of thoſe, who firſt did ſee it. For the ſame quantity of galls mingled with ſo much com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon water, or any other Fountain water thereabouts, will not alter it any thing at all; unleſſe to theſe you alſo adde vitrioll, and then the colour will appear to be of a blewiſh violet, ſomewhat inkiſh, not reddiſh, as in the former, which hath an exquiſite and accurate con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>junction of other Mineral exhalations, beſides the vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trioline. But this probation will not hold, if ſo be you make triall with the ſaid water being carried farre from the Well; by reaſon of the preſent diſſipation of his ſpirits.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="9" type="chapter">
                  <head>
                     <hi>CHAP. IX.</hi> Of the properties and effects of Vitrioll, according to the ancient and modern Writers.</head>
                  <p>THE qualities of <hi>Vitrioll,</hi> according to <hi>Dioſcorides, Galen, Aetius, Paulus Aegineta,</hi> and <hi>Oribaſius;</hi> are to heat and dry, to bind, to reſiſt putrefaction, to give ſtrength and vigour to the interiour parts, to kill the flat worms of the belly, to remedy venemous muſhroms, to preſerve fleſh over moiſt from corruption, conſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the moiſture thereof by its heat, and conſtipating by his aſtriction the ſubſtance of it, and preſſing forth the ſerous humidity.</p>
                  <p>And according to <hi>Matthiolus</hi> in his Commentaries upon <hi>Diſcorides,</hi> it is very profitable againſt the plague and peſtilence, and the chymicall oyle thereof is very available (as himſelf affirmeth to have ſufficiently proved) againſt the ſtone and ſtopping of Urine, and many other outward maladies and diſeaſes, (<hi>Ander<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacus</hi> and <hi>Geſner</hi> adde to theſe the Apoplexy) all which, for avoiding of prolixity, I do here purpoſely omit.</p>
                  <p>Neither will I further trouble the Reader with the
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:135135:8"/> recitall of divers and ſundry excellent remedies, and medicines, found out and made of it in theſe latter times, by the Spagyrick Phyſitians, and others: Inſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much that <hi>Joſeph Quercetanus,</hi> one of thoſe, is verily of opinion, that out of this individual mineral, well and exquiſitly prepared, there might be made all man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of remedies and medicines ſufficient for the ſtoring and furniſhing of a whole Apothecaries ſhop.</p>
                  <p>But it will (perhaps) be objected by ſome one or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in this manner: If vitrioll, which as moſt do hold, is hot and dry in the third degree, or beginning of the fourth, nay, of a cauſtick quality and nature (as <hi>Dioſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corides</hi> is of opinion) ſhould here be predominant; then the water of this Fountain muſt needs be of great heat and acrimony; and ſo become not onely unprofitable, but alſo very hurtfull for mans uſe to be drunk, or in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardly taken.</p>
                  <p>To which objection (not to take any advantage of the anſwer, which many learned Phyſitians do give, <hi>viz.</hi> that vitriol is not hot, but cold) I ſay: Firſt, that although all medicinall waters doe participate of thoſe minerals, by which they do paſſe, yet they have them but weakly <hi>viribus refractis</hi> (eſpecially when in their paſſages they touch, and meet with divers other mine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rals of oppoſite tempers and natures.</p>
                  <p>Secondly, I Anſwer, that in all ſuch medicinall Fountains as this, ſimple water doth far ſurpaſſe and exceed in quantity, whatſoever is therewith intermixed, by whoſe coldneſſe it commeth to paſſe, that the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary is ſcarce, or hardly perceived. For example, take one proportion of any boyling liquor to 100. or more, of the ſame cold, and you will hardly find in it any heat it all. Suppoſe then vitrioll be hot in the third degree, it doth not therefore follow, that the water which hath his vertue chiefly from it, ſhould heat in the ſame de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree. This is plainly manifeſt not onely in this foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain, but alſo in all others, which have an acide taſte,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:135135:9"/> being indeed rather cold then hot, for the reaſons a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove mentioned.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="10" type="chapter">
                  <head>
                     <hi>CHAP. X.</hi> Of the effects which this Fountain worketh, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duceth in thoſe who drink of it.</head>
                  <p>EXperience ſheweth ſufficiently, beſides reaſon, that this water firſt, and in the beginning cooleth ſuch as uſe it: But being continued, it heateth and drieth; and this for the moſt part it doth in all, yet not alwayes. For (as we ſhall more fully declare af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards) it effecteth cures of oppoſite, and quite con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary natures, by the ſecond and third qualities where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with it is endowed; curing diſeaſes both hot, cold, dry, and moiſt.</p>
                  <p>Thoſe waters (ſaith <hi>Renodaeus</hi>) which are repleniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with a vitrioline quality, as thoſe at the <hi>Spaw,</hi> doe preſently heal, and (as it were) miraculouſly cure diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſes, which are without all hope of recovery; having that notable power and faculty from vitrioll; by the vertue and efficacy whereof, they paſſe through the meanders, turnings and windings of all parts of the whole body. Whatſoever is hurtfull, or endammageth it, that they ſweep and carry away: what is profitable and commodious, they touch not, nor hurt: that which is flaccid, and looſe, they bind and faſten: that which is faſtned, and ſtrictly tied, they looſe: what is too groſſe and thick; they incide, diſſolve, attenuate, and expell.</p>
                  <p>More particularly the water of this fountain hath an inciſive and abſterſive faculty to cut and looſen the vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcous and clammy humours of the body, and to make meable the groſſe: as alſo by its piercing and penetra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting power, ſubtilty of parts, and by his deterging and deſiccative qualities to open all the obſtructions, or oppilations of the meſentery (from whence the ſeeds of moſt diſeaſes doe ariſe and ſpring) liver, ſpleen; kid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neys,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:135135:9"/> and other interiour parts (and which is more to be noted and obſerved) to coole, and contemperate their unnaturall heat, helping and removing alſo all the griefs and infirmities depending thereupon.</p>
                  <p>Beſides all this, it comforteth the ſtomack by the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtriction it hath from other minerals, eſpecially Iron, ſo that (without doubt) of a thouſand, who ſhall uſe it diſcreetly, and with good advice (their bodies firſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing well and orderly prepared by ſome learned and skil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Phyſitian, according to the ſtates thereof, and as their infirmities ſhall require) there will ſcarcely be any one found, who ſhall not receive great profit thereby.</p>
                  <p>Moreover, it cleanſeth, and purifieth the whole maſſe of blood contained in the veynes, by purging it from the ſereſity peccant, and from cholerick, phlegmatick, and melancholike humours, and that principally by Urine, which paſſeth through the body very clear, and in great quantity, leaving behinde it the mineral forces, and vertues.</p>
                  <p>Their ſtooles, who drink of it, are commonly of a blackiſh, or dark green colour, partly becauſe it empti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth the liver and ſpleen from aduſt humours, and me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lancholy, or the ſediment of blood; but more eſpecially, becauſe the minerals intermixed do produce and give ſuch a tincture.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="11" type="chapter">
                  <head>
                     <hi>CHAP. XI.</hi> In what diſeaſes the water of this Fountain is moſt uſefull and beneficiall.</head>
                  <p>OVer and beſides the peculiar and ſpecifical faculties, which this fountain hath, it ſheweth divers and ſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dry other manifeſt effects and qualities in evacuating the noxious humours of the body, for the moſt by Urine, eſpecially when there is any obſtruction about the kid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neyes, ureters and bladder: Or by Urine and ſtoole both, if the meſentery, liver, or ſpleen, chance to be obſtructed. But, if the effect or grief be in the matrix
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:135135:10"/> or womb, then it cleanſeth that way according to the accuſtomed and uſuall manner of women.</p>
                  <p>In melancholly people it purgeth by provoking the haemorrhoides, and in cholerick by ſiege or ſtool. If it cauſeth either vomit or ſweat, it is very ſeldom &amp; rare.</p>
                  <p>See here a moſt admirable work guided by the om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nipotency and wiſdome of the Almighty, that a natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall, clear, and pure water, ſhould produce ſo many and ſeverall effects and operations, being all of them in a manner contrary one to another, which few me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicines compoſed by Art can eaſily perform without hurt and dammage to the party. Wherefore being drunk with thoſe cautions and circumſtances neceſſari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly required thereunto, it is to be preferred before ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny other remedies, as not onely procuring theſe evacu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ations; but alſo (which is more to be noted) ſtaying them when they grow ro any exceſſe. For ſeeing that here are minerals contained booh hot, cold, dry, apper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cive, aſtringent, &amp;c. there is none ſo ſimple, but muſt needs think and grant, that it cannot otherwiſe be, but good and wholſome in grievances and diſeaſes, which in their own natures are oppoſite:</p>
                  <p>But I may inſtance in ſome few, for which it is good and profitable, and therein obſerve ſome order and me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thod; It dryeth the over moiſt brain, and helpeth the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vils proceeding there from, as rhumes, catarhs, palſies, cramps, &amp;c.</p>
                  <p>It is alſo good and available aginſt inveterate head<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aches, megrims, turnings and ſwimmings of the head and brain, dizzineſſe, epilepſie, or falling ſickneſſe and the like cold and moiſt diſeaſes of the head.</p>
                  <p>It cheareth and reviveth the ſpirits, ſtrengtheneth the ſtomack, cauſeth a good and quick appetite, and furthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth digeſtion.</p>
                  <p>It helpeth the black and yellow Jaundies, and the evil which is accompanied with ſtrange fear and exceſſive ſadnes, without any evident occaſion or neceſſary cauſe,
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:135135:10"/> called <hi>Melancholia</hi> or <hi>Hypocondr aca.</hi> Likewiſe the ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chexy, or evil habit of the body, and the dropſie in the beginning thereof, before it be too far gone. For beſides that it openeth obſtructions, expelleth the redundant water in the belly, and contemperateth the unnaturall heat of the Liver.</p>
                  <p>It cooleth the Kidneys or Reins, and drive forth ſand, gravel, and ſtones out of them, and alſo hindereth the encreaſe or breeding of any new, by the concretion and ſandering of gravel, bred of a viſcous and clammy hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mor or ſubſtance, the ſame it performeth to the bladder for which it is alſo beneficiall, if it chance to have any evil diſpoſition either in the cavity thereof, or in the neck of it, and ſhutting muſcle called <hi>Sphincter,</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by the whole part or member, is let and hindered in his office and function.</p>
                  <p>Moreover if there chance to be any ulcer in the parts laſt ſpecified, or any ſore, or fiſtula in <hi>perinao</hi> through an impoſtume ill cured, this water is a good remedy for it in regard of its cleanſing, cicatricing and conſtringing power and vertue; and for that cauſe it is very proper &amp; commodious for the acrimony and ſharpnes of Urine, and againſt the ſtopping and ſuppreſſion of Urine, dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficulty of making water, and the ſtrangury.</p>
                  <p>Although it is very available againſt the ſtone in the Kidneys, and againſt the breeding and increaſe of any new there; yea and againſt little ones, that are looſe in the bladder; yet notwithſtanding it will afford little or ſmall benefit to thoſe, in whom it is grown to be very great and big in the bladder: becauſe nothing will then ſerve to break it, as <hi>Braſſavolus</hi> ſaith, but a ſmiths anvil and hammar. Nevertheleſſe, if in this caſe inciſion be uſed, it will be very commodious, both for mundifying and conſolidating of the wound, made for the extracti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of it.</p>
                  <p>It ſhall not be needfull to ſpeak much of the profit, which will enſue by the fit adminiſtration of it in the inveterate venereous <hi>Gonorrhaea</hi> cauſing to ceaſe and
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:135135:11"/> ſtay totally, and correcting the diſtemper, and the ulce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous diſpoſition of the ſeed veſſels, and the vicine parts.</p>
                  <p>There are very few infirmities properly incident to women, which this water may not ſeem to reſpect much. The uſe whereof, after the advice and councel had of the learned Phyſitian, for the well and orderly prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring their bodies, is ſingular good againſt the green ſickneſſe, and alſo very commodious and behovefull to procure their monethly evacuations, as alſo to ſtay their over much ſlowing; as well to correct, as to ſtay their white floods; as well to dry the womb being too moiſt, as to heat it being too cold, through which cauſes and diſtempers conception (for the moſt part) is let and hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered in cold Northern Countries, as <hi>England</hi> and the like. For by the help of it theſe diſtempers are changed and altered, the ſuperfluous humidities and mucoſities are taken away, the part is corroborated, and the reten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive vertue is ſtrengthned.</p>
                  <p>This hath been ſo much, and ſo often obſerved at the ancient <hi>Spaw,</hi> that it cannot otherwiſe, but be alſo ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rified at this in after times, when it ſhall be frequented (as thoſe have been) with the company of Ladies, and Gentlewomen: Divers whereof, having been former<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly barren for the ſpace of ten, twelve years, or more, and drinking of thoſe waters for curing and helping ſome o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther infirmities, then for want of fruitfulneſſe, have ſhortly conceived after their return home to their hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bands, beyond their hopes and expectations.</p>
                  <p>Beſides all this, it is good for thoſe women, who, though otherwiſe apt enough to conceive, yet by reaſon of the too much lubricity of their wombs, are prone to miſcarry and abort, if before conception they ſhall uſe it with thoſe cautions and directions requiſite.</p>
                  <p>Alſo it reſpecteth very much the hard ſcirrhous and cancarous tumours, and the grievous ſoars and dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous Ulcers of the matrix. All theſe excellent helps and many more it performeth to women with more ſpeedy
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:135135:11"/> ucceſſe, if it be alſo received by injection. But here by the way, all ſuch women, who are with child, are to be admoniſhed, that they forbear to uſe it during that time.</p>
                  <p>In children it killeth and expelleth the worms of the guts and belly, and letteth and hindreth the breeding, and new encreaſe of any more.</p>
                  <p>I will here forbear to write any thing of the benefits which it affordeth againſt old and inveterate itches, mohphews, leproſies, &amp;c. in regard the other three ſulphurous fountains, before mentioned, do more pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly reſpect ſuch like grievances. Neither will I now ſpend any more time in ſhewing what vertues it hath in the cure of the Indian, commonly called the French, or rather Spaniſh diſeaſe: becauſe experience hath found out a more certain and ſure remedy againſt it.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="12" type="chapter">
                  <head>
                     <hi>CHAP. XII.</hi> Of the neceſſity of preparing the body before the uſe of this water.</head>
                  <p>IT is not in moſt things the bare and naked know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge or contemplation of them, that makes them profitable to us; but rather their right uſe, opportune, and fit adminiſtration. Medicines are not ſaid to be <hi>Deorum Manus,</hi> that is, the hands of the Gods, as <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rophilus</hi> calleth them, or <hi>Deorum dona;</hi> that is, the gifts of the Gods (as <hi>Hippocrates</hi> believed) till they be fitly applyed and ſeaſonably adminiſtred by the counſel and advice of the learned and skilfull Phyſitian, according to the true rules, and method of Art.</p>
                  <q>
                     <l>Temporibus medicina valet, data, tempore proſunt,</l>
                     <l>Et data non apto tempore vina nocent.</l>
                  </q>
                  <p>That is,</p>
                  <q>
                     <l>Medicines availe in their due times,</l>
                     <l>And profit is got by drinking wines.</l>
                     <pb n="20" facs="tcp:135135:12"/>
                     <l>In timely ſort; but all in reaſon.</l>
                     <l>They do offend, drunk out of ſeaſon.</l>
                  </q>
                  <p>Therefore to know the originall minerals, faculties, and vertues of this worthy acide fountain, will be to no end, or to ſmall purpoſe for them, who underſtand not the right and true uſe, nor the fit and orderly admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration of it. For not onely Phyſick or medicines, but alſo meats, and drinks taken diſorderly, out of due time and without meaſure, bringeth oftentimes detriment to the party, who otherwiſe might receive comfort and ſtrength thereby: So likewiſe this water, if it be not drunk at a convenient time and ſeaſon, in due faſhion and proportion: yea, and that after preparatives, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſite purgings, and evacuation of the body, may eaſily hurt thoſe, whoſe infirmities otherwiſe it doth princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pally reſpect. For medicines ought not to be taken raſhly and unadviſely, as moſt do hand over head with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any conſideration of time, place, and other circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances; as that ignorant man did, who getting the receit of that medicine, wherewith formerly he had been cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, made trial of it again long after for the ſame infir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity without any help or good at all; whereat greatly marvelling, received this anſwer from his Phyſitian: I confeſſe (ſaid he) it was the ſelf ſame medicine but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe I did not give it, therefore it did you no good.</p>
                  <p>To the end therefore that no occaſion may hereafter be either given or taken by the miſgovernment, or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver-raſhneſſe of any in uſing it to calumniate and tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce the worth, and goodneſſe of this fountain, I will briefly here ſhew what courſe is chiefly to be followed and obſerved by thoſe who ſhall ſtand in need of it.</p>
                  <p>Firſt then, becauſe very few men are throughly and ſufficiently informed concerning the natures and cauſes of their grievances, it will be neceſſary that every one ſhould apply himſelf to ſome one or other, who either out of his judgement or experience, or both, may truly be able to give him counſell and good advice concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:135135:12"/> the conveniency of this fountain. And if he ſhall be adviſed to uſe it, then let the party (in the fear of God) addreſſe himſelf for his way to it, againſt the fit ſeaſon of it, without making any long and tedious daies journeys, which cauſe laſſitude, and wearineſſe.</p>
                  <p>Then, being come to the place, he ought after a dayes reſt, or two, to have his body well prepared, and gently cleanſed with eaſie lenitives, or purgatives, both fit and appropriate, as well to the habite and conſtitution thereof, as alſo for the diſeaſe it ſelf, and as occaſion ſhall require, according to the rule of method, which teacheth that univerſal or general remedies ought ever to precede and go before particulars. Now what theſe are in ſpeciall, to fit every ones caſe in particular, is im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible either for me here, or any elſe to define preciſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly. <hi>Ars non verſatur circa individua.</hi> We may ſee it true in mechanical trades. No one Shoomaker can fit all by one Laſt: nor any one Taylor can ſuit all by one, and the ſelf ſame meaſure.</p>
                  <p>Yet in regard it may perhaps be expected that ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing ſhould be ſaid herein, I ſay, that in the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning (if occaſion ſerve) ſome eaſie Clyſter may very fitly be given, as well for emptying the lower inteſtines from their uſuall excrements, as for carrying away and cleanſing the mucoſe ſlimes contained therein. After that, it will be convenient to prepare the body by ſome Julep or Apozeme, or to give ſome lenitive medicine to free the firſt region of the body from excrements. For otherwiſe the water might peradventure convey ſome part of them, or other peccant matter, which it findeth in his paſſage either into the bladder, or to ſome other weak and infirm member of the body, to the increaſe of that evill diſpoſition, which is to be removed, or elſe to the breeding of ſome other new infirmity.</p>
                  <p>Some perhaps will here object and ſay, that the time of the year, in which this fountain will be found to be moſt uſefull, will be the hotteſt ſeaſon thereof; or (if you liſt ſo to call it) the dog-days, when it will be no fit time to purge at all.</p>
                  <pb n="22" facs="tcp:135135:13"/>
                  <p>To this I anſwer and ſay: Firſt, the purging me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicines here required are not ſtrong, and generous, but gentle, mild and weak, ſuch as are ſtyled <hi>Benedicta medicamenta:</hi> which may with great ſafety and profit be given either then or at any other time of the year without any danger, or reſpect of any ſuch like cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtance at all.</p>
                  <p>Secondly I anſwer; although this obſervation of the Dogdayes might perhaps be of ſome moment in hotter Countries, as <hi>Greece</hi> where <hi>Hippocrates</hi> lived, who firſt made mention of thoſe dayes: yet in colder climates, as <hi>England,</hi> and ſuch like Countries, they are of little or ſmall force at all and almoſt not to be regarded any whit, either in uſing mild and tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perate purgatives, or almoſt in any other; or in blood-letting, though very many, or moſt do erroniouſly ſay and think the contrary. So that (if there be cauſe) they may as well and ſafely then purge, as at any other time: Or if occaſion ſhall urge, as in plethoricall bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies, and many other caſes, a vein may ſafely (or ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther moſt commodiouſly) be then opened, and ſo much blood taken away, as the skilfull Phyſician ſhall think in his diſcretion and wiſdom to be needful and requiſite.</p>
                  <p>Let no man here think that this is any ſtrange poſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion or a new paradox (for the learned know the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary) or that I am ſtudious of innovation, but rather deſirous to root out an old and inveterate error, which in all probability hath coſt moe Engliſh mens lives, than would furniſh a royall army, in neglecting thoſe two greater helps or remedies, to wit Purging and Blood-letting in hot ſeaſons of the year; which in all likelihood might have ſaved many of their lives, while expecting more temperate weather, they have been ſummoned in the mean time, or <hi>interim,</hi> by the meſſenger of pale death to appear in another world.</p>
                  <p>Wherefore let all thoſe who are yet living, be admo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed hereafter by their examples, not obſtinately and
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:135135:13"/> wilfully to eſchew and ſhun theſe two remedies in hot ſeaſons, and in the time of the Dog-dayes, (much leſſe all other manner of Phyſicall helps) not once know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſo much as why, or wherefore, and without any reaſon at all, following blind and ſuperſtitious tradition and error, haply firſt broached by ſome unworthy and ignorant Phyſician, not rightly underſtannding <hi>Hippo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crates</hi> his ſaying in all likelyhood, or at leaſt wiſe miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>applying it: which hath ſo prevailed in theſe times, that it hath not onely worn out the uſe of purging, but alſo of all other Phyſick for that ſeaſon, becauſe moſt people by the name of Phyſick, underſtand purging onely, and nothing elſe; as though the Art and Sci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of Phyſick was nothing elſe, but to give a potion, or purge. Then we rightly and truly might ſay, <hi>Filia devoravit matrem.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>But foraſmuch as moſt people are altogether igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant of the true ground or reaſon, from whence this ſo dangerous an error concerning the Dog-dayes, did firſt ſpring and ariſe, give me leave a little to go on with this my digreſſion, for their better inſtruction and ſatisfaction; and I will briefly and in few lines, ſhew the caſe and miſtake ſomewhat more plainly.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Hippocrates</hi> in his fourth Book of <hi>Aphoriſmes,</hi> the fifth, hath theſe words: <hi>Sub canicula, &amp; ante canicu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lam, difficiles ſunt purgationes.</hi> That is, under the ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicular, or Dogſtar, and before the Dog-ſtar purga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions are painfull and difficil. This is all that is there ſaid of them, or brought againſt them for that ſeaſon or time of the year. A great ſtumbling block againſt which many have daſhed their feet and knockt their ſhins, and a feafull ſcar crow, whereat too many have nicely boggled. Here you do not find or ſee purging medicines to be then prohibited, or forbidden to be given at all (much leſſe all other Phyſick) but onely ſaid to be difficil in their working partly becauſe (as all expoſitors agree) nature is then ſomewhat enfeebled
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:135135:14"/> by the heat of the weather; partly becauſe the humours being then, as it were, accended, are more chaffed by the heat of the purging medicines; partly, and laſtly, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe two contrary motions ſeem then to be at one and the ſame time, which may offend nature; as the great heat of the weather leading the humours of the body outwardly to the circumference thereof, and the medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cine drawing them inwardly to the center. All which circumſtances in our cold region are litle, or nothing at all (as formerly hath been mentioned) to be regard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. For as <hi>Jacobus Hollerius,</hi> a <hi>French</hi> Phyſitian, much honoured for his great learning and judgment, hath very well obſerved in his Comment upon this Apho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſme; <hi>Hippocrates</hi> ſpeaketh here onely of thoſe purg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing medicines which are ſtrong and vehement, or hot and fiery; and that this precept is to take place in moſt hot Regions, but not in theſe cold Countries, as <hi>France, England</hi> and the like.</p>
                  <p>Over and beſide all this, thoſe churliſh hot purging medicines, which were then in frequent uſe in <hi>Hippo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crates</hi> time, and ſome hundred years after, are now for the moſt part obſolete, and quite grown out of uſe, ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome brought in practice by Phyſitians in theſe dayes; becauſe we have within theſe laſt ſix hundred years, great choice and variety of more milde, benigne, and gentle purgatives found out by the <hi>Arabian</hi> Phyſitians, which were altogether unknown unto the Antients, to wit, <hi>Hippocrates, Dioſcorides, Galen, &amp;c.</hi> which have little heat and acrimony, many whereof are temperate, and divers cooling, which may moſt ſafely be given ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in the hotteſt times and ſeaſons of the year, or in the hotteſt diſeaſes. Let us adde to theſe the like fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liar and gentle purging medicines more lately, yea al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt daily newly found out ſince the better diſcoveries of the Eaſt and Weſt Indies. So that henceforth let no man fear to take either eaſie purgatives, or other inward Phyſick, in the time of <hi>Canicular</hi> or Dog-dayes.</p>
                  <pb n="25" facs="tcp:135135:14"/>
                  <p>The ſame <hi>Hollerius</hi> goeth on in the expoſition and interpretation of the ſame Aphoriſme, and confidently ſaith: <hi>Over and beſides that we have benigne medicines, which we may then uſe, as Caſſia, &amp;c.</hi> We know and find by experience, no time here with us more whole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome and more temperate (eſpecially when the <hi>Eteſian</hi> or <hi>Eaſterly</hi> windes do blow) then the <hi>Canicular</hi> dayes, ſo that we finde by obſervation, that thoſe diſeaſes which are bred in the moneths of <hi>June</hi> and <hi>July,</hi> do end in <hi>Auguſt,</hi> and in the <hi>Canicular</hi> dayes. Wherefore if a diſeaſe happen in thoſe dayes, we fear not to open a vein divers times, and often, as alſo to preſcribe more ſtrong purging medicines.</p>
                  <p>Wherefore away hence forth with the ſcrupulous conceit, and too nice fear of the Dog-dayes, and let their ſuppoſed danger be had no more in remembrance among us. And if any will yet remain obſtinate, and ſtill refuſe to have their beams pulled out of their eyes, let them ſtill be blinde in the midſt of the clear Sun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhine, and groap on after darkneſſe: and let all learned Phyſitians rather pitty their follies, then envy their wits.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="13" type="chapter">
                  <head>
                     <hi>CHAP. XIII.</hi> At what time of the year, and at what houre of the day it is moſt fit and meet to drink this water.</head>
                  <p>TO ſpeak in generall terms, it is a fit time to drink it, when the ayre is pure, clear, hot and dry: for then the water is more tart, and more eaſily digeſted, then at other times. On the contrary, it is beſt to forbear, when the ayre is cold, moiſt, dark, dull and miſty: for then it is more feeble, and harder to be concocted.</p>
                  <pb n="26" facs="tcp:135135:15"/>
                  <p>But more ſpecially, the moſt proper ſeaſon to under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take this our <hi>Engliſh Spaw</hi> diet, will be from the mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt or latter end of <hi>June,</hi> to the middle of <hi>September,</hi> or longer, according as the ſeaſon of the year ſhall fall out to be hot and dry, or otherwiſe.</p>
                  <p>Not that in the Spring time, and in Winter it is not alſo good, but for that the ayre being more pure in Sum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer, the water alſo muſt needs be of greater force and power. Notwithſtanding it may ſometime ſo happen in Summer, that by reaſon of ſome extraordinary falling of rain, there may be a ceſſation from it a day or two. Or if it chance to have rained over night, it will then be fit and neceſſary to refrain from drinking of it, untill the rain be paſſed away again: or elſe (which I like better) the Fountain laded dry, and filled again, which may well be done in an houre, or two at the moſt.</p>
                  <p>Touching the time of the day when it is beſt to drink this water, queſtionleſſe the moſt convenient hour will be in the morning, when the party is empty and faſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing about ſeven a clock: Nature having firſt diſchar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged her ſelf of daily excrements both by ſtoole and U<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rine, and the concoctions perfected. This time is like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe fitteſt for exerciſe, which is a great good help, and furtherance for the better diſtribution of the water, whereby it doth produce its effects more ſpeedily.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="14" type="chapter">
                  <pb n="27" facs="tcp:135135:15"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>CHAP. XIV.</hi> Of the manner of drinking this water, and the quantity thereof.</head>
                  <p>THoſe who deſire the benefit of this Fountain, ought to go to it ſomewhat early in the morning; and, if they be able and ſtrong of body, they may doe very well to walk to it on foot, or at leaſt wiſe ſome part of the way. Such as have weak and feeble legs, may ride on horſe-back, or be carried in the Coaches, or born in Chairs. As for thoſe whoſe infirmities cauſe them to keep their Beds or Chambers, they may drink the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter in their lodgings, it being ſpeedily brought to them in a veſſel or glaſſe well ſtopt.</p>
                  <p>It is not my meaning or purpoſe to deſcribe here par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularly what quantity of it is fit and meet for every one to drink: for this is part of the task and office which belongeth to the Phyſitian, who ſhall be of coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell with the Patient in preparing and well ordering of him: who is to conſider all the ſeverall circumſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, as well of the malady or diſeaſe it ſelf, as of his ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bit and conſtitution, &amp;c. Nevertheleſſe I may adviſe, that at the firſt it be moderately taken, increaſing the quantity, daily by degrees, untill they ſhall come at laſt to the full height of the proportion appointed, and thought to be meet and neceſſary. There they are then to ſtay, and ſo to continue at that quantity, ſo long as it ſhall be needfull. For example, the firſt morning may happily be ſixteen or eighteen ounces, and ſo on by degrees to 20, 30, 40, 50, 60. or more, in people who are of good and ſtrong conſtitutions. To<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the ending the abatement ought likewiſe to be made by degrees, as the increment was formerly made by little and little.</p>
                  <p>Here by the way every one muſt be admoniſhed to take notice, that it is not alwayes beſt to drink moſt, leſt they chance to oppreſſe and overcharge nature, that
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:135135:16"/> would rather be content with leſſe. It will therefore be more ſafe, to take it rather ſomewhat ſparingly, though for a longer time, then liberally and for a ſhort time. But, indeed, the trueſt and juſteſt proportion of it, is ever to be made and eſteemed, by the good and laudable concoction of it, and by the due and orderly voiding of it again.</p>
                  <p>It will not be here amiſſe to adde this one obſervati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on further: That it is better to drink this water once a day, then twice, and that in the mornings, after that the Sun hath dried up, and conſumed the vapours re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained through the coldneſſe of the night, &amp;c. as is for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly declared. After drinking it, it will be needfull to abſtain from meat and other drink for the ſpace of three or four hours.</p>
                  <p>But if any one, who hath a good ſtomack, ſhall be deſirous to take it twice a day; or if any ſhall be neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſarily compelled ſo to doe for ſome urgent cauſe, by the approbation of his Phyſitian, let him dine ſomewhat ſparingly, and drink it not again, untill five hours af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter dinner be paſt, or not untill the concoction of meat and drink in the ſtomack be perfected: Obſerving like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, that he content himſelf in the afternoons with al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt half the quantity he uſeth to take in the mornings.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="15" type="chapter">
                  <head>
                     <hi>CHAP. XV.</hi> Of the manner of dyet to be obſerved by thoſe, who ſhall uſe this water.</head>
                  <p>THe regiment of life in meats and drinks, ought chiefly to conſiſt in the right and moderate uſe of thoſe, which are of light and eaſie digeſtion, and of good and wholeſome nouriſhment, breeding laudable juyce. Therefore all thoſe are to be avoided, which beget crud and ill humours. There ought furthermore ſpeciall notice to be taken, that great diverſity of meats and diſhes at one meal is very hurtfull, as alſo much condiments, ſauces, ſpice, fat, &amp;c. in their dreſſing and cookery.</p>
                  <pb n="29" facs="tcp:135135:16"/>
                  <p>I commend hens, capons, pullets, chickens, partridge, pheſants, turkies, and generally all ſuch ſmall birds, as live in woods, hedges, and mountains. Likewiſe I doe approve of veal, mutton, kid, lamb, rabbets, young hare or ſeverits, &amp;c. All which (for the moſt part) are rather to be roaſted then boyled. Nevertheleſſe thoſe, who are affected with any dry diſtemper, or thoſe, who other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe are ſo accuſtomed to feed, may have their meats ſodden, but the plainer dreſſing the better.</p>
                  <p>I diſcommend all ſalt meats, beef, bacon, pork, lard, and larded meats, hare, veniſon, tripes, and the entrails of beaſts, puddings made with blood, pig, gooſe, ſwan, teal, mallard, and ſuch like; and in generall all wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter-fowle, as being of hard digeſtion and ill nutri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
                  <p>Amongſt the ſeveral kinds of fiſhes, trouts pearches, loaches, and for moſt part, all ſcaly fiſh of brooks, and freſh rivers may well be permitted. Moreover ſmelts, ſoals, dabs, whitings ſturbuts, gurnets, and all ſuch o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, as are well known not to be ill, or unwholeſome to feed on. All which may be altered with mint, hyſſop, aniſe, &amp;c. Alſo cre-fiſhes, crab-fiſh, lobſters, and the like, may be permitted.</p>
                  <p>Conger, ſalmon, eels, lampries, herrings, ſalt-ling, all ſalt fiſh, ſturgion, anchovies, oyſters, cockles, muſcles, and the like ſhel-fiſh are to be diſallowed.</p>
                  <p>White-meats, as milk, cruds, cream, old cheeſe, cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtards, white-pots, pudding-pies, and other like milk-meats, (except ſweet butter, and new cream cheeſe) are to be forbidden. Soft and reer eggs we do not pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hibit.</p>
                  <p>Raiſons with almonds, bisket-bread, marchpane-ſtuff, ſuckets, and the like, are not here forbidden to be ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten.</p>
                  <p>Let their bread be made of wheat, very well wrought fermented or leavened; and let their drink be bear well boyled and brewed; and let it be ſtale, or old
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:135135:17"/> enough, but in no wiſe tart, ſharp, or ſower: And above all, let them forbear to mix the water of the fountain with their drink at meals; for that may cauſe many in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conveniences to follow and enſue.</p>
                  <p>Let me advice them to eſchew Apples, Pears, Plumbs Codlings, Gooſeberries, and all ſuch like ſommer fruits, either raw, in tarts, or otherwiſe: Alſo peaſe, and all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther pulſe; all cold ſallets, and raw hearbs; onions, leeks, chives, cabbage or coleworts, pompons, cucum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers, and the like.</p>
                  <p>In ſtead of cheeſe at the end of meals, it will not be amiſſe to eat citron, or lemon pils condited, or elſe fen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nel, anniſe, coriander comfits, or biskets and carawayes, as well for to diſcuſſe and expell winde, as to ſhut and cloſe the ſtomack, for the better furthering the digeſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of meats and drinks. And for that purpoſe, it would be much better, if the Phyſitian, who is of counſell, ſhould appoint and ordain ſome fit and proper Tragea in groſſe powder mixed with ſugar, or elſe made into little cakes or morſels. Likewiſe marmalade of quinces either ſimple or compound, (ſuch as the Phyſitians do often preſcribe to their patients) may be uſed very com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modiouſly.</p>
                  <p>After dinner they ought to uſe no violent exerciſe, neither ought they to ſit ſtill, ſadly, heavy and muſing, nor to ſlumber and ſſeep; but rather to ſtir a little, and to raiſe up the ſpirits for an hour or two, by ſome fit recreation. After ſupper they may take a walk into the fields, or Caſtle yard.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="16" type="chapter">
                  <head>
                     <hi>CHAP. XVI.</hi> Of the Symptomes or accidents, which may now and then chance to happen to ſome one or other in the uſe of this water.</head>
                  <p>ALthough thoſe who are of good and ſtrong conſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutions, obſerving the aforenamed direction, do ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:135135:17"/> or never receive any harm, or detriment by drin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king this water: notwithſtanding it may ſometime ſo fall forth, that ſome of the weaker ſort may perhaps ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve ſome little, or ſmall inconvenience thereby, as re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention of it in the body: inflation of the belley: co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtiveneſſe, and the like. Wherefore to gratifie thoſe, a word or two of every one ſhall ſuffice.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. Then, for to cauſe a more ready and ſpeedy paſſage of it by Urine, it will not be amiſſe to counſel the party after his return to his lodging, to go to his naked bed for an hour or two, that thereby warmneſs and natural heat may be brought into each part of the body, the paſſages more opened, and nature by that means made more fit and apt for the expulſion of it. During which time it will be very requiſite to apply hot cloaths to the ſtomack: but not ſo as to provoke ſweat. Or elſe, to cauſe it to void and evacuate either by urine, ſtool, or ſweat, exerciſe will be a good help and furtherance; if the party be fit for it. But if neither of theſe will pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vail, then a ſharp glyſter ought to be adminiſtred.</p>
                  <p>The inflation or ſwelling of the belly hapneth prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipally to thoſe, who have ſeeble and weak ſtomacks; who may do very well to eat anniſe, fenel, or corriander comfits at the fountain between every draught, and to walk a little after; or elſe ſome carminative Lozenges, made with groſſepowders, ſpices and ſeeds for breaking of wind: or what other thing the learned Phyſitian ſhall deem to be moſt fit and proper in his wiſdome and judgment. But if the inflation chance to be very great, then a carminative glyſter muſt be ordained.</p>
                  <p>Such as ſhall be very coſtive may doe well to eat moiſtning meats, and to uſe mollifying hearbs, raiſons ſtoned, corants, damaſcene prunes, butter, or the yolks of eggs, and the like in their broths, or pottage. If theſe will not be ſufficient, then let a day be ſpared
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:135135:18"/> from drinking the water, and let the party take ſome lenitive medicine, laxative corants, or ſome ſuch like thing; whereof the Phyſitian hath ever great choice and variety, wherewith he can fit directly every one his caſe; to whom preſent recourſe ever ought to be had, when any of theſe, or the like accidents do happen, as likewiſe in all other caſes of waight and moment.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="33" facs="tcp:135135:18"/>
               <head>A Relation of certain particular Cures, Done by vertue of Mineral waters, neer <hi>Knaresborow</hi> in the Weſt-riding of the County of Yorkſhire.</head>
               <byline>By Mr. <hi>Michael Stanhope.</hi>
               </byline>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>EFORE entrance be made into the enſuing Narrations, it will not be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſe for the ſatisfaction of ſuch who are meer ſtrangers to the knowledge of theſe waters, to let them know, that it is now full ſix years ſince no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice hath been given to the world by a Book called <hi>Spadacrene,</hi> or the <hi>Engliſh Spaw,</hi> (writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten by Dr. <hi>Deane,</hi> a learned Phyſitian of the City of <hi>York</hi>) of certain Mineral waters, ſeated in the Forreſt of <hi>Knaresborow,</hi> in the Weſt riding of <hi>Yorkſhire.</hi> Since which time divers have repaired to them from remote places, (according to their ſeverall neceſſities) to experiment them, invited by the Doctors promiſed probabilities of their uſefull operations. What hath been the event and ſucceſſe, I have undertaken to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent to the publick view.</p>
               <p>That <hi>Spaw</hi> Springs though they uſually challenge (as doth the <hi>Spaw</hi> in <hi>Germany,</hi> which is the reaſon we give them the ſame name) a ſingularity in eaſing and curing (ſuch as are curable) of the Stone and Gravel, as alſo in opening the obſtructions of the Spleen, and allaying all Melancholy effects and paſſions, yet it will appear by the ſubſequent Diſcourſe and Relations, that this kinde of water hath other rare and ſecret influences and operations, which hath procured no ſmall wonder in thoſe who have obſerved the effects; the particular
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:135135:19"/> inſtances whereof, (without any longer ſuſpending thy expectation) I now intend to enter upon, beginning firſt with the cure and alleviation of the ſtone, and other diſtempers incident to the Kidneys and Reins.</p>
               <p>In the year 1626. Miſtreſſe <hi>Rolf</hi> of <hi>Hadley</hi> in the County of <hi>Suffolk,</hi> having occaſion to give a viſit to ſome of her neer friends in <hi>Yorkeſhire,</hi> within a few weeks of her ſtay there, ſhe found her ſelf ſuddenly ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prized with extraordinary ſharp fits, which by their ſymptoms did manifeſtly appear to be the ſtone. Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon ſhe applied her ſelf to the Phyſitians advice, but finding little or no eaſe by their preſcriptions (though probable ones) ſhe was perſwaded to try the new wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter at <hi>Knaresborow,</hi> where ſhe had not continued above a fortnight, but ſhe voided many ſtones, to the number of an hundred bigger and leſſe, whereby ſhe was quit of all her pain, and hath ever ſince continued in health, free from all manner of annoyance in that kinde.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Henry Curra</hi> of <hi>Whardale</hi> in the Weſtern parts of <hi>Yorkeſhire,</hi> ſervant to Sr. <hi>Peter Middleton,</hi> about the age of 50 years, having ſuffered much pain for divers years, his fits of the ſtone being ſo violent, that he was not able to rid on horſe back, or to ly in his bed an hour together without riſing, nothing that he could take affording him any eaſe, he went at laſt to the <hi>Spaw</hi> Spring, where having drunk the water about a month, he voided divers ſtones, ſome whereof he hath to ſhew, being bigger then a great Pea. He returned home ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed of all his pain, he recovered his ſtrength, and is now well able to ride about his occaſions without any diſturbance, nor hath he ever ſince (being now three years) had any fits worthy of complaint.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Henry Rowly</hi> of <hi>Linton,</hi> near <hi>Weatherby</hi> in <hi>Yorke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhire,</hi> of the age of ſixty years, much perplexed a long time with the ſtopping of his water, by his repair to the <hi>Spaw,</hi> voided much gravell, and from that time was no more troubled ſo long as he lived:</p>
               <pb n="35" facs="tcp:135135:19"/>
               <p>Miſtreſſe <hi>Barker</hi> of <hi>Doare</hi> in <hi>Darbeſhire,</hi> about the age of 34 years, had a dangerous ulcer in her Kidney, beſides a very obſtructed body, wherewith ſhe was brought ſo low, that ſhe was not able to go without the ſupport of one or two; her ſtomack had loſt its appe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tite, not able through weakneſſe to digeſt any meat, no nor the moſt apt broaths that could be made, ſo that ſhe was forced to ſuſtain nature by returning to her in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fant pap. In this weak and deſperate condition (ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving formerly not ſpared to uſe all the helps that could be deviſed by the Phyſitian) ſhe was gently brought to the <hi>Spaw,</hi> not expecting (as ſhe told me her ſelf) to be recovered, onely ſhe thought it not fit to be wanting to any means that might be propounded. It pleaſed God to give ſuch a bleſſing in the uſe of the water (which ſhe daily drunk as well as ſhe was able) that within a few dayes there came from her an incredible deal of putrid matter, which gave her ſuch eaſe, that by degrees ſhe gathered ſtrength, her inward parts were deopilated, her ſtomack reſtored, and within the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſe of five weeks ſhe was (to the wonder of all that had taken notice of her) reduced to a moſt apparent ſtate of health and ability of body. I ſeeing her this Summer, 1631. at the <hi>Spaw,</hi> (for it was the foregoing year ſhe had received her Cure, and this year came onely to the water to confirm her ſelf) could not but admire to behold ſo freſh a look, and ſo well-liking a body, conſidering the report of her former exceeding weakneſſe.</p>
               <p>I will not ſay it were time loſt, but it might be better ſpent then to multiply all the known examples in this kind, the foregoing ones being of ſufficient proof to make good the waters efficatious uſe in the infirmity of the ſtone. Not that I am to ſeek for more, for I might (but that I willingly avoid ſuperfluous tediouſnes) adde to the other.</p>
               <pb n="36" facs="tcp:135135:20"/>
               <p>Miſtreſſe <hi>Ellis,</hi> wife to Mr. <hi>Ellis</hi> Miniſter at <hi>Beaver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ley,</hi> who received a wondrous cure in the like ulcerated part.</p>
               <p>Miſtreſſe <hi>May,</hi> a Citizens wife of <hi>York,</hi> who after many years trouble, (being of great age) was abſolutely freed from her long continued fits of the ſtone, with di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers others whom I purpoſely omit (nothing being more ordinary) that others may come into play (though of a differing kind, yet) of remarkable note.</p>
               <p>For Melancholy and Splenetique effects, there are few or none (that I have ever yet heard of, who have repaired to this <hi>Spaw</hi> water, but have found extraordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary eaſe, and a great abatement of thoſe diſturbances which are the ordinary unwelcome attendants of that diſtemper.</p>
               <p>Amongſt others Mr. <hi>Sacheveril</hi> of <hi>Derbiſhire</hi> (hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of this <hi>Spaw</hi> water) came to <hi>York</hi> to adviſe with D. <hi>Dean,</hi> who after he had fitly prepared his body (a rule groſly omitted by many) ſent him to <hi>Knaresborow</hi> to drink of the water, being in the year 1630, to his great relief. For whereas he had been exceedingly long time perplexed with many fearfull paſſions, and upon ſlight occaſions apt to entertain horrid and aſtoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhing imaginations, (the ordinary companions of that diſeaſe called <hi>Hypochrondriaca paſſio</hi>) he returned to <hi>York</hi> to give D. <hi>Deane</hi> thanks for his ſending him to the water, profeſſing his ſpirits to be much cheared, his fancy cleared from all cloudy and miſty conceits, which his very look and inſpection did witneſſe, and ſo he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turned home, continuing ever ſince in a conſtant tenor of a quiet and uninterrupted condition.</p>
               <p>Miſtreſſe <hi>Ayre,</hi> wife to M. <hi>Anthony Ayre</hi> of <hi>Rampton</hi> in <hi>Nottinghamſhire,</hi> a Gentlewoman of much worth and eſteem for her approved vertue, and all other re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>requiſites that give luſtre to her Sex, had (with the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pence of much money) tried what could be done in the taming and qualifying of that ſame dull melancholly
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:135135:20"/> humour, her ſelf not unſeen (as in many rare ſecret ſo) in curious receits of that kind, at length grew weary in trying concluſions, receiving little or no benefit by any. She was drawn at laſt by report of the <hi>Yorkeſhire Spaw,</hi> to try the effects of it, which was in the year 1629. where ſhe found more comfort and caſe by one months uſe of the water, then ſhe could ever receive by all the beſt adviſe her money could purchaſe.</p>
               <p>Others I have known affected or rather afflicted in this kind, who have acknowledged to have received great benefit by this water, whoſ names &amp; ſtories I ſpare, the forenamed being ſufficient inſtances of the power<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full effect of this water in moderating this ſame <hi>Ludi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brium Medicorum,</hi> the melancholly humour.</p>
               <p>I ſhall now preſent a miſſellany of other cures, or rather wonders, worthy the ſerious conſideration of the learned, and the admiration of all.</p>
               <p>M. <hi>William Thompſon</hi> Poſtmaſter of <hi>Weatherby</hi> in <hi>Yorkeſhire,</hi> had continued deſperately ſick of a hectick feaver 28 weeks, living then in <hi>Cambridge ſhire.</hi> He had uſed the advice of the beſt Phyſitians in thoſe parts, and was at laſt given over as a man paſt hope, his weaknes being ſuch, that he went not to ſtool in all that time, but by the help of a ſuppoſitory, or the like means. In this poore eſtate (hearing of this water) he adventureth in the depth of winter (a moſt unſeaſonable time by the conſent of all thoſe who write of the uſe of theſe kind of waters) to experiment them, and ſo with ſome difficulty he was brought to <hi>Weatherby</hi> being diſtant from <hi>Kna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>resborow</hi> four miles. Having reſted a day or two, he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan to drink of the water, which had ſuch good effect in him, that without any pain at all he had the benefit (the firſt day) of nature, and within a few days he found a ſtrange alteration in his body, his ſtomack was quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, and his ſpirits ſtrangly revived. He continued the drinking of the water 14 dayes, till at length he was not ſenſible of any defect that might cauſe him to make any longer uſe of it.</p>
               <pb n="38" facs="tcp:135135:21"/>
               <p>To be ſhort, within a ſmall time (through Gods bleſſings) meerly by this water, he was reſtored to be a perfect man, and ſo continueth. This was in 1628.</p>
               <p>Mr. <hi>Foules</hi> a gentleman of <hi>Scotland,</hi> and advocate of <hi>Edenborow,</hi> about the age of 57. years, through a weakneſſe of all his limbs proceeding (as may be ſuppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed from a relaxation of the ſinews, was not able (but with much trembling) to lift his hand to his mouth, or to get on, or off his horſe, but with much help, he came to <hi>Knaresborow</hi> in the year 1627. where having ſtaid about a moneth, drinking every morning of the <hi>Spaw</hi> ſpring, and making uſe of the Sulphur water by way of bath at his lodging, before he departed he was able to perform all fit offices about himſelf, without the aid of any, and hath continued in good ſtate of body ever ſince.</p>
               <p>Mr. <hi>Rauden</hi> of <hi>Rauden</hi> in <hi>Yorkeſhire,</hi> had been ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny years ſoar vexed with terrible pangs, and gripings in his body, ſo that through the continuall extremity of his diſtemper, his fleſh was decayed, his appetite loſt, and his ſleep very ſhort and unquiet. He had uſed the adviſe of ſome of the beſt Phyſitians of the Kingdome, but finding little or no eaſe, he came to try what the <hi>Spaw</hi> water would doe, being then but newly divulged. Not many dayes after he had drunk of the water, he avoided two great chains of worms, being either of them above a yard long, which though they ſeemed di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers worms linckt together, by ſeveral motions in many parts at once (which had they been, would have a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mounted to thouſands) yet were but one, of which the learned report that kind of worm to be of a ſtrange and ſcarce credible length. About four dayes after he voy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded 4 other ſingle worms, great &amp; very long, but dead: After which he voided no more, but was freed from all manner of pain, and by degrees and ſteps aſcended a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain to his former beſt health, and hath continued a a ſound man ever ſince.</p>
               <pb n="39" facs="tcp:135135:21"/>
               <p>The confident knowledge hereof invited a Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man (a neighbour of his) called <hi>Rockley,</hi> having conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nued long a very infirm man, and not able by any means to underſtand the cauſe of his weakneſſe, to try the water, where after he had ſtaid a few dayes, there came from him fourteen worms, or rather <hi>Monſtra</hi> as ſome will term them, every one about an inch long and alive, their heads were black, and their tails tipt with black, all of them having many feet, about 6 dayes after he voided 4 more of the like form alive: Moſt of them he kept alive in a box a few dayes which were ſeen of many, with no little wonderment. Since which time he hath recovered ſtrength, and liveth now in very good health.</p>
               <p>The Lady <hi>Vavaſor</hi> (wife to Sir <hi>Tho. Vavaſor</hi> Baro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>net of <hi>Yorkſh.</hi>) had loſt in a manner the uſe of all her limbs through what diſtemper I know not, but ſhe was brought to ſuch a degree of weakneſſe, that child like ſhe was rockt in a cradle: there were no means unaſſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed which might re-inable her, but all in vain. In this e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate ſhe was brought to the <hi>Spaw</hi> water, by the uſe whereof (by Gods mercy) ſhe was reſtored to ſtrength and health.</p>
               <p>One <hi>William Shan</hi> of <hi>Medley</hi> in <hi>Yorkſhire,</hi> being much troubled with the ſtopping of his water, which cauſed intollerable pain, in a deſperate method in one of his fits (being a man of extraordinary courage) cauſed an inſtrument of Iron to be made by an ordinary ſmith about the bigneſſe and length of a pack-needle. This (not any other daring to do it) he (boldly rather than wiſely) thruſt up into his yard, and pulling it forth vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lently, he opened the paſſage, ſo that a great quantity of water with an intermixture of blood iſſued forth, by reaſon of a dangerous wound made by the inſtrument, which after proving ulcerous, could by no means be healed. He (at his laſt refuge) repaired to the <hi>Spaw</hi>
                  <pb n="40" facs="tcp:135135:22"/> water, where within a few dayes he received not onely cure of his former ſtoppage of water, but was perfectly cured of his ulcer.</p>
               <p>One <hi>Walles</hi> of <hi>Copeland</hi> in the County of <hi>Northum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berland,</hi> about the age of fifty years, being of an extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinary corpulency of body, his belly eſpecially of a vaſt greatneſſe. For divers years he had not been able to go the ſpace of an hundred yards (eſpecially if it were an aſcent) without reſting himſelf, his breath failing him upon the leaſt extraordinary motion. By the drin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of the <hi>Spaw</hi> water he was brought to that paſſe within three weeks, that his belly did fall to an ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ſize, he was able to go from the Town of <hi>Knaresbo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row</hi> to the Spring (which is a mile and a half, part of it being a great aſcent) without any deſire of eaſe, and hath continued ever ſince a man as able to foot it, as moſt of his age.</p>
               <p>The like effect the late Right Honourable Counteſs of <hi>Buckingham</hi> found, who this laſt Summer 1631. vouchſafed to honor the <hi>Northern Spaw</hi> with her pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence. Her infirmity (I have it from her own mouth) was a ſhortneſſe of breath, not being able to get up an ordinary pair of ſtairs, but with much difficulty of brea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, and reſting once at the leaſt. There is none will queſtion but her ample fortune was able to command the choiceſt helps of Phyſick: Which failing ſhe had recourſe to <hi>Wellingborow,</hi> but even that water (ſo much famed) was not able to perform any thing worth her ſtay. At laſt ſhe was adviſed by a learned Artiſt (who was no ſtranger to this our <hi>Spaw</hi>) to make tryall of our water. Her Honor was pleaſed to tell me (having drunk orderly of the water about ten dayes) that ſhe found the whole frame of her body reduced to a very good tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, and for that particular, which occaſioned her com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the water, ſhe did profeſſe ſeriouſly, that ſhe was well able to mount two pair of ſtairs without either ſupport, or the leaſt deſire of reſpite. The time of the
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:135135:22"/> year was ſomewhat too far ſpent at her coming to the water (for it was the middle of <hi>Auguſt</hi>) ſo that the cold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of the air and frequent ſhowers, forc'd her depar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture before the water could finiſh its work, which was no ſmall prejudice to her after being.</p>
               <p>Mrs <hi>Fairweather</hi> of the City of <hi>York,</hi> dwelling in <hi>Micklegate</hi> had been long troubled with a dizineſſe in her head (call it the <hi>Vertigo</hi> or what you pleaſe) ſo that if ſhe did but ſtoop to the ground (looking downwards) ſhe was ready to fall; by the uſe of the <hi>Spaw</hi> water for the ſpace of a month was abſolutely freed from this her diſtemper.</p>
               <p>The Lady <hi>Hoyl</hi> wife to the new Lord Mayor of the City of <hi>York,</hi> after ſhe had been the mother of four children, did fall into a ſtrange infirmity. Her face (for the moſt part every ten or eleven weeks after ſhe had conceived) did ſwell and grow very red, many knots ariſing in divers parts of her face. The ſwelling ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times was ſuch that it almoſt deprived her (for the time) of her ſight: during the continuance of which trouble ſhe miſcarried of three or four children toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. It muſt be ſuppoſed one of her ability (being hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py alſo by enjoying a tender loving husband) could want no means that part could afford, but no proof or good ſucceſſe was found. She was at laſt adviſed to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pair to the <hi>Spaw,</hi> where ſhe ſtayed about three weeks, finding apparent ſignes of her bodies alteration. Within two moneths of her return home, it pleaſed God ſhe conceived, continuing in a conſtant ſtate of health to the time of her delivery. She hath ſince then been bleſt with diverſe children, not having the leaſt touch of her former diſtemper.</p>
               <p>A poore boy about the age of 13 years, had often ſtrange fits like thoſe of the <hi>Epilepſie,</hi> or falling ſicknes, yet ſomewhat differing from the ordinary fits of that diſeaſe, neither ſoaming at the mouth, nor ſhewing any diſtortions of countenance. He would lye (as if he had
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:135135:23"/> been dead) the ſpace of a quarter of an hour, without the leaſt motion. In this caſe he had continued a year and more, and did uſually fall two or three times a day. He was brought to drink of the <hi>Spaw</hi> water, and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in ten dayes did ſo alter, that he did not fall above once in ſix dayes ſpace. He returned home in hope of reco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very, yet too ſoon if my advice might have taken place; but the party that brought him thither, told me he was not able to ſtay in regard of the charge.</p>
               <p>Miſtreſſe <hi>Sadler</hi> daughter to that ſame reverend Sage of the Law, Sir <hi>Edward Cook</hi> (let her pardon me that I cloſe the relations of the <hi>Spaw</hi> with her name, who for her worth and excellent parts deſerved to be rank'd and equalled with the beſt of her ſex) came to the <hi>Spaw</hi> in the year 1630. Her diſtemper, (as near as I can inform my ſelf) was a long continued fixed pain in her head: It is very probable that ſhe received benefit by the waters uſe, which incouraged her to repair to the water again the laſt year 1631. And pitty it were ſhe ſhould not find good ſucceſſe, ſhe ſhewed her ſelf ſo rare a pattern of patience, in attending the iſſue of ſix weeks ſtay, not any one that I have obſerved, proceeding in the whole courſe in drinking of the water, with ſuch conſtant obſervation of all thoſe Rules which are requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſite to be obſerved, by thoſe who expect the benefit by the water.</p>
               <p>And now having finiſhed what I think fit to inſtance concerning this our <hi>Spaw</hi> water, I will adde a few ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periments of the Sulphur Spring.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Maud Bogge</hi> (for by that name ſhe is commonly known) a woman of an ordinary condition, dwelling in the City of <hi>York,</hi> about the age of 50 years, had a ſwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling about her ancle, which had continued long: the place was for the moſt part, very red and hard, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto was applyed divers means by the Surgeons to bring it to a head, but nothing availed. Her pain did daily increaſe, the part was grown monſtrouſly great,
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:135135:23"/> whereby ſhe began to loſe the uſe of her limb. She was at length adviſed to go to the Sulphur Spring near <hi>Knaresborow,</hi> whither (with much ado) ſhe was brought on Horſe-back. The next day after her coming, ſhe drunk liberally of the water, which purged her in a vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>olent manner, and at night ſhe bathed her leg in the water at her lodging. This courſe ſhe continued three days, during which time the ſwelling abated very much, and ſhe was able the fourth day to tread on the ground ſo boldly and firmly that without expecting any further operation of the water, ſhe returned to the City of <hi>York</hi> on foot, as if ſhe ſcorned any other help, and within a week ſhe was ſo perfectly cured, that divers who had ſeen her ſweld leg, did admire to ſee her trot up and down the City, as if ſhe never had ailed any thing. This was in the year 1627. This Summer being 1631. I ſpoke with her at <hi>York</hi> from whom I had her ſtory. D. <hi>Dean</hi> and divers in <hi>York</hi> taking ſpeciall notice of it.</p>
               <p>In 1629. there came a poor man to make uſe of the <hi>Sul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phur</hi> Spring, whoſe name and abode I have not had the opportunity to learn. He had a great ſwelling in his knee which had continued long; be place was exceding hard to feel too, and grown over with hair nor could the force of any medicine make it to yield to any abate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment or ſuppuration. He drunk of the water daily, w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> purged him, and bathed his legge often in it, within leſſe than a fortnight the part did ſenſibly ſoften, and ſoon after did break; whence iſſued a great number of ſmall worms, to the amazement of divers. Freed from theſe he was much refreſhed, and in few days returned home, by all appearance a ſound man. A noble Knight [S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
                  <hi>F.F.</hi>] (who lived then near <hi>Knaresborow</hi>) took (as there was good cauſe) ſpeciall notice of this ſtrange cure) whoſe unblemiſhed reputation is a ſufficient war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant to ſatisfie me in the publiſhing of it.</p>
               <p>One <hi>Benſon</hi> who dwelleth near the Spring, aſſured me a poor woman had received the like cure in one of her breaſt whereof he was a witneſſe.</p>
               <pb n="44" facs="tcp:135135:24"/>
               <p>There is nothing more familiar then for poor people to repair to this Spring, moſt of them (that have the pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience to ſtay) receiving cure of old ſores, and ulcerated parts. What inward diſeaſes this water doth properly reſpect, hath not yet (which is great pity) been judici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly examined: but that it may be uſefully applyed, this one following inſtance may fully ſatisfie.</p>
               <p>One <hi>Smith,</hi> a Shoomaker dwelling in the City of <hi>York,</hi> was extremely overgrown with the Scurvy, ſo that he was in ſome danger of his life, uſuall medicines no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing availing. He was at length adviſed by a learned Scholler in the City (by profeſſion a Divine, yet verſed of late in Phyſical notions) to ſend for the Sulphur Spring water to his houſe, which he not very willingly did, thinking it a hard task to drink water in the cold of Winter. His ordinary draught was half a pint in the morning, which had ſuch good ſucceſs in him, that with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in leſſe than a month he was by this and other means, quit of this diſeaſe.</p>
               <p>The like effect a good old man in the City experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mented to his great relief.</p>
               <p>Lo here two Springs of admirable operations! And if an exact Sumetritian by the proportion of <hi>Hercules</hi> his foot, be able to collect the whole fabrick of his body, why may not the learned (whoſe ſerious thoughts are bent upon the Theory of Natures ſecrets) from theſe examples deduce excellent concluſions of large and ample uſe.</p>
               <p>I had thought to ſhut up this Diſcourſe, but that I am loath to ſmother any thing that may tend to the publick good.</p>
               <p>Thoſe who have obſerved the wonders of this our happy Iſle, have taken notice of a Spring ſeated un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derneath the Caſtle of <hi>Knaresborow,</hi> commonly called <hi>The dropping Well,</hi> famous for the turning of whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver is caſt into it, or caſually falls in (as moſſe, leaves, ſticks, and the like) into ſtone: whereupon it is that this
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:135135:24"/> Spring is viſited of many by way of admiration. But time hath of late diſcovered a Phyſicall uſe of this wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, namely that it is an infallible cure for a flix.</p>
               <p>This year 1631. it was my chance to be a witneſſe of this particular, A Miniſter of <hi>Yorkſhire,</hi> one <hi>Greatheed,</hi> came to <hi>Knaresborow</hi> to give his attendance on a No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Gentlewoman, whoſe infirmity did crave the aid of the <hi>Spaw</hi> water: He (not intending to drink of the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſeriouſly) thought he might ſafely now and then (as many do for companies ſake) take a few draughts of the <hi>Spaw</hi> Water: within a weeks ſtay (by what accident I know not) he was overtaken with a violent flix, which continued three dayes in ſuch a degree of exceſſe, that there was juſt cauſe to fear. At that time there was hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pily in the houſe a Phyſician of good note, one Dr <hi>Web</hi> (a Gentleman of extraordinary curious parts, beſides his exact knowledge in his profeſſion, to whom thoſe <hi>Northern</hi> waters are indebted for his carefull examina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of them, and his willingneſſe to advance their due fame) whoſe advice being craved, (and time it was to adviſe, for the party was brought ſo weak, that he was ſtept into a degree of convulſions) he (out of former ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience in a noble Lady in the ſame caſe, who (all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther means failing) had preſent help by this <hi>Dropping Well</hi>) preſently cauſed him to drink a draught of the ſaid water, which without dallying inſtantly ſtayed the flix, ſo that within a few dayes he became a ſtrong man.</p>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
